This video describes how to prepare the child and mother or carer before performing the fundal red reflex tests in both newborns and older children.
The child should be held securely yet comfortably, either on the lap, over a shoulder, or, if a baby, lying on their back.
It is important for them to feel safe. Young babies can be restless and may need to be swaddled.
Examining shortly after a feed can help as they will be relaxed and a little sleepy.
Older children may settle by playing with a toy for a short while.
Speak with a friendly tone and try to get down to their eye level.
Explain what you are going to do and gain consent before you start.
First, ask the mother or carer if they have seen anything wrong with their child's eye or vision and how long they have noticed the problem.
Next, look at the child's face and eyes. Ask yourself some questions.
Does the child seem to have pain in one or both eyes? Are the eyes open or are they keeping them tightly shut?
Is there watering or discharge from the eyes? Are the eyes the same size? Are the eyelids swollen?
Now, consider how the child is seeing. Move your face slowly from side to side, watching their eyes.
Make some silent smiles. Does the child follow the movement of your face or respond to your silent smile?
Again, ask yourself some questions. Do both eyes move freely and together?
Are the eyes straight or is one eye turning inwards or outwards? Do the eyes wobble?
You can also use the lights on the Arclight and picture targets to gain attention and assess the quality of vision.
Move the target side to side, up and down. Look to see if the child is fixing and following the target.
Can they reach and point accurately at the target?
Often, only one eye cannot see well. You or the mother can cover one eye, then the other.
Move the target and compare how the child behaves to when using both eyes, then one at a time.
If the child does not like one eye being covered, it suggests the uncovered eye does not see so well.
If you think you can see something wrong with the external eye, look more closely using the loupe end of the Arclight.
Switch the lights on and move up close to around 6 cm. You may need to use your finger to gently open the eyelids.
Ask yourself some questions. Is the white part of the eye pink or red? Is the pupil or cornea grey or white?
Is the pupil round? Can you see any foreign bodies? Now you are ready to perform the reflex tests.